so I'd like to just for good luck I'd
like to read the
text uh in in the original
language My teacher asked me to write a
text
inban and then translate it and they
said I should start doing that
so you get that all right all right here
we go
say then I'd like you to repeat with me
ready next page
sorry we got to do that
again this is Miller
style okay just so you know I mean it's
not as weird as it sounds okay
okay so we finished the first uh verse
yesterday and we didn't really get on to
the second verse yet right we have to
speed up a
bit never is going to happen Okay
uh in the first verse uh we were we
heard the
description
of the heart chakra
opening uh in the period following the
direct perception of Ultimate Reality
right and then uh we heard about this
light colorless light like it's not like
a stream it's more like
a a bar or a
pole uh a very solid movement of
colorless light out of your
chest uh and that's the physical
Sensation that you have when the heart
chck opens okay it's of a colorless
light like a pillar but sideways of
colorless light coming out of your chest
okay and then we said
that because of that release of Prana at
the heart chakra then you have
a extraordinary
perception of in a single minute you see
the faces of billions upon billions of
living beings not just human okay there
are lots of other creatures running
around the universe okay and some of
them we can imagine and some of them you
can't okay some are hard to imagine
imagine a person who is so immense
physically and mentally that they
can uh play with galaxies like
marbles okay there are such beings
that's what they call Brahma or there
are people like that there are real
people like that and they are huge okay
they are not uh
enlightened they are huge suffering
beings but they get to play with
galaxies okay uh there are such things
so you see all the and on down to tiny
creatures in the ocean billions of
creatures in every square foot of water
and imagine that as the heart chakra
opens you are able to see the face of
every creature from these Galaxy players
down to the creatures in a few inches of
water sea water you can see all of them
in this world and then imagine that
multiply that times every inhabited
World there is which are infinite
there's no number there there are so
many planets where people live that this
very scene is being repeated on
countless planets as we
speak okay there's it because it's
infinite the odds are infinite okay
there's a guy sitting up there probably
he has hair or
something uh and
he's billions of the same person giving
the same talk at the same time because
the odds are infinite the odds are
infinite this talk is going
on in many worlds at this moment
different people okay who look like us
and then imagine that you could see all
of them at the same
time and love them have a feeling of
love for them and and want to meet them
and want to care for them as if they
were your
child I was with uh Lama Ora where is
Ora she went outside
probably uh I was there uh at the birth
you know they asked me would I like to
go I thought well I wouldn't like to go
but I'll go and uh and and then uh it
was in Tucson in one of those natural
birthing centers it took 72
hours I didn't make it I left after I
left after 2 days I stayed up for 2 days
and I I couldn't take it anymore and uh
you know I laugh you know but before
when she was pregnant I remember she was
doing a bunch of projects uh she was
cataloging all the acip text she was
cataloging 10,000 loose text that of
running around and uh I remember we took
a drive in a car with Peggy Hitchcock do
you guys know Peggy Hitchcock she's 85
80 something years old no 75
sorry uh so she was like in the front
seat and Ora was in the back and I was
driving and and and Peggy said well Ora
honey what what are you going to be
doing after the baby's born you know or
it's like oh I'm going to be cataloging
and I'm going to be doing all these
projects and she she turns around she
says
honey those hormones kick in you ain't
going to do anything but hug the
baby it was funny you know she's like
when those hor you ain't going to be
yourself anymore you just kiss the baby
all day you know hug the baby and it was
true it came true you know she just goes
around from country to Country hugging
the baby
and so just imagine you have that
emotion towards all the people you see
okay all the countless try to imagine
what it's like to see a few billion
faces not a
few uh at the same moment and love them
all like she loves the baby like you're
just like want to kiss her on the head
you know and that's about you try to
have a conversation with her it's kind
of
frustrating
uh she like
what then she kisses the baby again you
know and uh so try to imagine that kind
of a a love okay so that's sort of like
the goal of this class all right the
goal uh I would like to go through some
meditations and practices of the inner
body which would induce that kind of
experience okay because it's difficult
to induce that experience but it's it's
the goal of a life to have that
experience for 15 minutes 5 minutes then
then your life is worth the is worth it
your whole life becomes valuable and
well spent if you have 5 minutes of love
like that for countless living beings
okay then your whole life was worth it
okay all the trouble and all the work
for that five minutes it was worth it
okay and I would
I have this dream that you know
everybody in this room could have that
experience in this life okay and you can
induce that experience in two ways and
we talked about it one is uh meditations
you can do certain kinds of meditations
you can do certain kinds of
attitude adjustment meditations
emotional adjust you can know you can
work with your emotions and your your
mind okay you can do it that way
but you can work from the inside also
you can work from the inner body okay uh
you can change the inner body the
chakras and the channels and The
Prana and that will also induce this
kind of love right so wouldn't it be
cool to do
what just do both okay like work I don't
know I was in the diamond business for
many years okay and we had to the peak
of our business I had to find 30,000
diamonds a day okay and they might be of
the same size and the same quality okay
so out of two tons of ore you get one
Diamond I need 30,000 diamonds and they
have to match perfectly okay like
imagine that trying to find 30,000 okay
in one day that match and you you have
to go all over the world you have to
call people in in Bombay you call people
in Amsterdam you call people in Belgium
Anor you call people in Tel Aviv you go
to Singapore you go to Hong Kong you
call the whole world you have contacts
throughout the world each person gives
you six or seven stones 10 stones 20
stones and you collect them and and the
idea is that you you don't put your
hopes in one place you you go from many
angles to to get one goal you have to go
from many angles it's the same when you
want to open the heart chra
okay our goal is to open the heart
chakra you don't work at it from only
one angle you know you call
T which means you try to bring some wind
up the central channel to the heart
chakra then you call mumai which means
you try to bring some Prana down uh from
the upper chakras you see and then you
work on some
meditations like uh what we call the
seven
steps for developing love okay you you
work from the mental side uh to move The
Prana and then maybe you do
some yoga that is meant to address that
chakra okay so in in the study of Tantra
in in the Buddhist tradition one of the
principal commitments that a person is
asked to make is say chin
ch
ch okay you have to swear to that when
you Tak an empowerment in Tantra which
in my Monastery is not granted until you
finish
G okay that particular empowerment uh
you have to swear you have to promise uh
that you will chin on okay what does it
mean uh CH mean means uh I swear to use
outer
methods to develop the two great
realizations what are they one is the
direct perception of emptiness the
direct perception of higher reality
okay which if you see it for 15 or 20
minutes you are certain to become a be
an angel of Light somebody objected the
other day where were we Phoenix Phoenix
Phoenix they said why are you using this
Angel talk you know it's so Christian
you know and I said well that's exactly
what you are you know that's exactly
what you become you become an angel of
Light you know and I'm
sorry no I mean it's exactly the right
word okay you become like you become
that okay
so if you see emptiness directly for a
few minutes then the body will change
within a short time okay
uh so those two great those two two
great experiences see emptiness directly
see the faces of every being and love
them at the same time those two
experiences these are the goal of a
spiritual
life means you must induce those two
experiences by using inner and outer
methods okay both uh don't favor one
over the other use both okay Chi would
mean for
example if you wanted to now I'm going
to stop talking about developing
ultimate love okay I'm going to call it
opening your heart chakra but you know
what it means now okay it means love it
means that experience of Love coupled
just before it with the perception of of
the Ultimate Reality which is a long
story we're not going to go into that
okay
uh there are special yoga exercises in
the Buddhist tradition which I one one
time was linked with the Hindu tradition
in nor in in Bengal West Bengal uh the
tradition that shabi Joy or master aenar
or or all of their
kids uh like John friend or or David and
Sharon or all
those kids that have come from them all
of
those practices came from West
Bengal thousand years ago exactly a
thousand years ago and in those days uh
Hindus and Buddhists uh practiced
together and they practiced yoga
together and then uh that yoga came into
Tibet a thousand years ago um the main
two lineages of yoga that we practice
are called naropa and niguma say naropa
naropa and niguma so naropa was a
prince in India who by long story became
a monk and then became a Yogi and a
great uh practitioner of yoga and he was
taught a kind of yoga by his teacher
tilopa uh which included this six uh
yogas of of neuropa which includes the
practice of inner fire which has in it a
tiny sliver called the oenus of naropa
okay so physical yoga practice in Tibet
for in our Monastery is a tiny part of
the practices of inner fire which is
only one of the six yogas of nura okay
we study it that
way then his spiritual partner was
niguma he had a beautiful
beautiful uh spiritual partner it's one
of the Romeo and Juliet stories of
ancient India it's very
very I don't know I love the story and I
love them you know and uh it's just this
unbelievable story of two dedic at Yogi
Yogi and yogini who Liv their life
together and they practiced together and
they they T together and they were
unbelievable they so so beautiful and
their relationship was so beautiful and
so lady niguma
also had a whole system including a
system of yoga
okay and they came into Tibet a thousand
years ago lady niguma taught a a monk
named uh CH n and then her Aus came into
Tibet uh and then uh naropa Master
naropa taught uh marpa who was a beer
willing
businessman from tiet but a good yoga
practitioner and uh he brought it to
Tibet he taught it
to M who taught it to Guma and then it
comes down to us it came down to our
Monastery from them okay so an outer
method when you say
CH when you say I will practice both
inner and outer methods an outer method
would be to practice the yoga of niguma
okay sometimes she's called nigu say
nigu sometimes she's called
Neu and some some texts say her real
name was near gunma neara say neara
near means not Guna means a quality like
sat rajas tamas right and uh near near
Guna means she has no qualities she has
no nature it means the lady of emptiness
her it seems like her real name was the
lady of emptiness okay near
G so an outer method to open the heart
heart chakra would be for example The
Yoga practices the aenas of niguma okay
and and we'll talk about them okay what
the text says at this point verse
two uh Empress Neo okay Empress nego
means n all right you can use
her uh machine machine is a translation
of Tor say
toror Tor is a translation of the
Sanskrit
word
yantra yantra which means a magical
machine a magical
machine
or Contraption is a good word and uh
yoga inet is called magical machine Chun
yantra okay so you can study her
machine on the outside and then on the
inside you could use one of the
classical methods of opening your heart
okay and and the one that we'll be doing
is called uh
say means cause d means result m means
personal advice is which you receive
from a teacher dun means seven steps
okay so there are seven steps of a
meditation to opening your heart all
right so so what we're going to do is
open the heart from the inside and then
open the heart from the
outside and hopefully the two together
will open it okay all right and it's
very powerful you see some traditions
only have yoga Asus and some traditions
only have meditation but when you reach
the highest teachings of the Tibetan
tradition you are required to use both
at the same time you are required to do
yoga asanas to open the heart chakra and
and you are required to
do meditations which open your heart
okay and together they open the heart
chakra okay when the heart chakra opens
you have those two
experiences the the direct perception of
emptiness which changes your body into
that of an
Angel and the direct perception of all
the people of the universe and the love
and the knowledge that you will take
care of them okay that's
so I was sort of disappointing you guys
last night I don't
know supposed to be when you get to that
everybody starts crying or something you
know I try try to imagine
that you will be the person you your
career track is
inevitably unstoppably to become the
person who who takes care of every
single being on this planet it is your
destiny you it's Manifest Destiny you
will do that and you're worried about
you know you know your paycheck or on
your apartment or something like that I
mean you are meant for bigger things
okay you you
inevitably especially if you got here
inevitably you are destined to become
the person who takes care of every
single living creature on this planet
personally because once you get an
angel's body it's no problem to split it
okay you just clone yourself couple
billion times and you're standing next
to each person in the world caring for
them and taking care of their needs you
know
it's and that's a worthy way to spend
your life that's what you should be
doing that's what you want to be doing
this is just
frustrating uh working and and feeding
yourself and clothing yourself and
wiping your butt and you know these
things are all
like this you're frustrated you're not
happy cuz it it's not what you really
want to do you'd rather be an angel with
a few trillion bodies and and serving
people which is the most
fun so the way to get there is by inner
and outer means so we're going to talk
about both okay first half of this
class uh we'll concentrate on a
meditation uh this the seven step
meditation okay for the inside open the
heart make the heart feel
open and then after the break uh I think
we'll take a break and then we'll have
uh after the break not now okay don't
hope uh after the break we will do some
questions okay if you have any
questions uh I encourage you to ask you
can ask questions about what we covered
but also if you just have anything on
your mind or you have some kind of
personal
issue or personal problem the purpose of
these teachings is to
address the most serious problem you
have in your life right now okay so feel
free during the questions to
ask something that relates to your life
okay and something that you have some
kind of
a need or challenge going on in your
life and then we'll talk about it and
we'll work it out and and you
can it work okay so don't be don't ask
me some philosophical question if you're
having trouble with your
boyfriend okay because that becomes
philosophy all right so we'll take those
questions and then after that we'll go
into the inner body and I'm going to go
deeper into the inner body okay so we're
going to go a little deep and it will be
uh
detailed and um it will be things you
haven't heard before about the inner
body okay and they come come from
scriptures many many scriptures okay
they come from there are in
Tibet I don't
know uh there's over a thousand
scriptures on the inner body in the
cannon and then there are thousands more
commentaries inth there are many many
many
beautiful things uh to learn about the
inner body and there are many ways to
understand it and I'm just going to do
one of them with you okay very beautiful
really beautiful okay so we'll do that
after the break the the goal
being uh you have by tomorrow night by
the time we finish tomorrow night you
have an inner meditation to do which is
designed to open your heart and which
has been taught for over a thousand
years okay and then on the outside you
have a a practice of the body the phys
physical body which can move the chakras
open the chakras from the outside and
then you go at it from both sides all
right and and then that's the goal then
we'll see how many people go
into
labor we call it inducing labor not
you she's like do tomorrow or something
just hold out for a few days
uh so that's my plan so let's go to the
seven steps okay this is a seven step
and let me see if I remember say
Mar CH
chin s these are the seven very famous
uh steps okay we'll go through them one
by
one the first one is I think the most
difficult maybe uh uh it's called Marche
okay
mar mar means I acknowledge or I
recognize that you are my mother okay I
I see that you are my mother
okay and I put a very extensive reading
I gave you a very extensive reading I
think it's the most beautiful
presentation there are there are many
presentations of these seven steps the
one I lik the most was by
uh he was born in
1878 he was
the he taught my teacher
briefly uh when my teacher was very
young okay uh and but mainly he trained
uh CH who is the the root llama of the
present darling llama okay so the
present darling llama's teacher
is also uh my teacher's
teacher and uh his
teacher uh he he wrote a beautiful uh
piece about the seven steps and to me
it's the most beautiful one I've seen so
I translated it and you have it okay I
hope they have it right yeah okay thanks
to the okay they don't get these things
they get these things in the car from
Chinatown and uh they they pull it off
so I'd like to thank all the the people
doing
the and a lot of people uh helping me
personally uh all through the day I just
throw the the files at people and they
turn them into Tibetan and they they all
do it in the car or uh we gave a whole
presentation today where was that que
queens or something to the to the
Chinese Community uh of New York and
that was nice um but they do all this
work constantly they don't get any rest
uh and then they're going to do it again
tomorrow in a different continent and
then the next day you know so they they
work like that they're very
kind so Mar
means
uh look just just uh statistically okay
I used to think about it when I was a
little kid cuz I love science fiction
you know uh time is infinite okay time
has no beginning time has no end I mean
you can say big
bang uh you can put a number on it a
certain billion years ago think of it as
a single
drop in the history of the ocean uh
falling off the front of a wave and and
hitting the ocean's surface think of the
whole recorded history
of this universe as a single fall of a
drop from a wave in an ocean which which
has been going forever I mean to think
the world to think this big bang is the
first big bang come on it's naive you
know time
is unning time has no
beginning uh the
whole birth of the universe that that
scientists they're trying to measure
today right up in the space shuttle uh
space whatever orbiting
whatever uh that's just the most recent
burp of the universe come on it's it's
beginningless to it's naive to think
it's
only 30 billion years old you know
uh and all possible combinations have
already occurred you
have you it's naive to to think you come
here
once and then you don't come again or
you didn't come before I
mean isn't it if time is infinite if you
uh throw dice a trillion times it's
naive to think you will get 12 once you
know what I mean you you have been
here countless times there's no number
on the times you have been here and deep
down you know that you know you you
dimly some part of you remembers you
have been to this that's why people fear
death so much because they've been there
and they know what happens and they
don't want to go through it again okay
you that's why people have this
incredibly irrational fear of death okay
so you have been there countless times
and you know you know what's coming and
you know it hurts and you know what
happens afterwards so you you know that
you feel it you have been here countless
times which means that those of us in
this room we have had every relationship
with each other countless times okay we
talked about it last night okay you
have killed me countless times I have
killed you countless times we have been
married countless times I was your boss
countless times you were my boss
countless time okay I was a better boss
than you were
but
okay and uh we've done everything to
each other you know uh countless times
but the Beautiful thing is that I I have
been born from between your legs
countless times I have you have pushed
me out of your body countless times at
the risk of your life knowing that you
might die you gave me life countless
times okay
that's it's the way it is okay you have
okay and then they say uh in the
scriptures they say it's as if uh we had
both fallen off a ship and that ship was
caught in a whirlpool and then I see you
across the world pool going you know and
I'm going like this and I don't
recognize you anymore you know you're
the person who was on the ship with me
before I see you fly past in my life and
I don't realize I don't appreciate that
you you died countless times to give me
birth okay you have given me birth
countless times and you so just to
understand that is called Mari the first
step in the
meditation on developing love is to is
to
grasp
logically that everyone has been
everything to you and they have been
your mother and they have given their
life for you countless times okay my
llama when I first heard this I was in
in D Sala I was studying with
get 100 years ago and
uh and I remember he encouraged us he he
told us when you leave the class this
morning the first person you meet spend
some time thinking about who they that
they were your mother okay and we
weren't allowed to do it with another
student it had to be the first person we
met on the street outside the
class uh after the class we were
supposed to like spend some time with
them and and and see that and think that
they were our mother our own mother
before so me you know I went down to uh
lower D Sala and I ran into a Indian uh
biscuit seller with one of those little
carts you know and he's like got this
little towel on and no teeth you know
and he's old and he's kind of
cranky and and I he's the first person I
ran into you're going to have somebody I
don't know after the class
11:15 on 86 Street good luck uh so you
know I went out and I I ran into this
guy and I had to you know I had to spend
time with him and and think oh he was my
mother you know he's been my mother and
it was nice I remember it I still
remember it right it was very sweet uh
to spend time with him and just I didn't
tell him anything I just stood there for
a long time and and you know looked at
all his biscuits and then I was just
trying to get used to the idea that he
had been my mother okay that's called
step one that's Mary okay step
two is called chinen chinen means uh
just
reflect on how he took care of you when
he was your mother okay reflect on what
he did when he was your mother
okay and
uh okay my big mothering
experience I did a later I did a one
month Retreat uh up in flog stuff I
don't know early 9s right and uh this uh
lady and her husband helped me to buy
the groceries they found the place for
me when I had needs they would drop off
things once a week you know and so they
were very kind to me and they had two
small
boys so uh after I finished the retreat
I I I went to them and I said look I
know the boys are a lot of work I know
you never get any rest and I have a
proposal and they said what and I said
you guys go on a second honeymoon you
know I'll pay for it you go for a 3-day
weekend to some Resort and you spend
some time together
and you know and I'll watch the boys you
know I'll take care of the boys cuz I
knew they were all frazzled from the
kids you know and uh so then they they
were so happy they like dropped the kids
off the next day and uh I had all these
plans for them you know we were going to
make Mongolian Mouse trops together
which is a lot of fun they catch them
catch them Al you know and it's fun it's
like three sticks and a box and
and we made sticks and boxes and we were
having really good fun and then I'm like
I had to go to the bathroom you know and
I'm like okay you guys stay here I'm
going to the bathroom no we're coming to
with you you
know and I'm like well you know I kind
of want to go by
myself no we don't want you to go by
yourself and then I'm like finally I
just kind of got up fast and I ran in
the bathroom I I locked the door you
know and then I'm trying to poop you
know and they're banging on the door you
know like
hey it's really hard to poof when you
can't concentrate you know and they're
banging and they're screaming then they
start crying you know I'm like oh God
the neighbors are going to hear them and
they're going to hear the beating and
they're going to think something's going
on so I'm like pulling my pants up
coming out half done you know I'm like
you know sooner or later they have to
fall asleep right and uh they didn't
fall asleep you know and then I was like
oh my God you know it never occurred to
me that that parents never get a minute
like they don't get any time you know I
thought there must be some deal you know
where the kids go to the living room for
half an hour it's not like that and it
was really really terrible and uh and
then 2 Days Later the parents came I was
like oh my God
I said
D and cuz then even at night you're
worried about them you know like you
can't sleep you can't sleep fully you
kind of got to go like this you know and
uh you're worried like somebody's going
to choke themselves or someone's going
to sneak in or one of the kids is going
to walk out the door no you can't really
sleep either even at night you can't
sleep it's it's
unremitting uh just the name of the
lowest hell in
Buddhism
uh aii right un remitting so anyway uh
didn't it occur to me you know that they
never get any rest at all it's just
constant it's this constant pressure I
suppose even if you have a babysitter
and you go out for a movie or something
the pressure on your mind doesn't let up
you're still wondering is the babysitter
watching uh is one of those kids my
friend's
child took a what you call those little
hair butterfly hair clips and she pulled
it off and she swallowed the
spring and then she had this was pilar's
daughter and she had operations like all
day and cut her open and you know and
she almost died she's alive right she
she went into a combo but she survived
so you know I'm like watching them you
know like oh are there any Springs in
the house you know and then uh tiny
Springs like that and then the pressure
on your mind is uh unremitting there's
no rest you can't rest really and even
after they leave the house it's it's the
same I think parents never really rest
they their mind never really releases
from the child uh and they take care of
you they just care for you it's just un
it's just constant especially in the
first 3 years five years it's constant
there's no
break uh it's just like that
okay so the guy that's selling the
biscuits from the cart in dhava did that
for
me okay and now I curse you okay like
you're going to go out to 86 Street and
you're going to turn left or right but
you're going to run into
somebody and uh and I curse you you have
to think they did that for me
okay that person did that for me you
know
unremitting uh care and they did that
for me all right and so the first person
you see I curse you you will think of
that uh you will think of them taking
care of you uh like that all right and
you will remember when you teach this to
your own students which you must do okay
this is part of the deal I don't teach
things more than once
usually and the deal is that you have to
teach it next okay so then you're going
to talk about the guy you met on any6
okay I hope it's a good one uh to your
students okay and then uh that's step
number two okay Jin Jen means just think
about how she took care of you all right
how much she took care of you
chinin uh the third step of this
meditation is chin so say chin
so J so means uh pay their kindness back
do something to pay them back right even
in this life okay in
America it's not like say
China uh we don't appreciate our mothers
that much I think most of us it's kind
of popular in America to have a complex
about your mother and she was okay for
the first six years and then she
wouldn't let you do
something and then uh maybe at some
point she got hard on you or she she got
unhappy or she didn't treat you nice and
then you never forgive
her and now she drinks too much or
she's uh she's cranky and and and you
don't like her and you don't like to be
around her cuz she's so demanding and
then in this country there's not much of
a
culture of wanting to serve your
parents to repay them for the kindness
they gave you okay but in in other
countries it's not like that in China
it's very sweet okay in India it's
really sweet I had a diamond dealer
friend and um he lived in a place called
juu right which is like Hollywood in
Mumbai all the wealthy people live there
you're talking multi-millionaires
billionaires okay so he he's a diamond
dealer he he built a house in juu a huge
house uh Marvel floors gold toilet
fixtures pure gold and uh and then I
went to see him and he he stuffed in
with his family in this little apartment
uh inside the city and I'm like what are
you doing didn't you build a house he
said yeah I build a house and I said why
are you staying in this little apartment
you know and he said my father I said
what about your father he said he's over
there he he likes to stay in this little
room the room is like a closet
they had their father in like a little
room like a closet you know and I said
what's what's going on with him and he
says well he's old he can't talk he
doesn't he doesn't do anything we take
care of him and I said well take care of
him in the big house he doesn't want to
go he wants to stay here you know so I
said well can't you guys just go over
there and somebody watch and you can
hire 15 people to watch him you know
they said no no we can't do that he's
our father he's my father he wants to be
here we have to take care of him you
know and they did they took care of him
and it was beautiful and then they
couldn't sleep in there there was no
room to sleep and they slept on the
balcony uh outside under the stars the
two kids and the two parents they slept
on one they just laid out beds and slept
together it really beautiful you know
and uh they lived that way for a long
time cuz Dad didn't want to go you know
and they respected him and uh that's a
beautiful thing okay so
someone however you feel about your
mother or your father and a lot of us
have complexes about our father or
mother or my mother hit me or my father
was drunk or he left us or he didn't
help support us or you have we have all
these things but but you can't deny the
basic kindness they have shown you for
the to bring you up and and to take care
of you it was constant
unremitting care okay so
Jin Soul means do something to pay them
back have some kind of feeling that you
would like to pay them back okay that's
number four three okay the uh fourth one
is called uh Yong Juma say Yong
Juma
Juma Juma means uh when you think about
someone you
love uh they look beautiful to you Yong
means uh
the person that you most love in this
world okay when you see them you just
feel happy right you feel tenderness or
affection for them a deep deep affection
the person you love most in this life
okay when you see their face or when you
come in their presence you feel this
this deep deep affection for them and
love for them Amora SEO right what is
that love is is blind you know you're so
in love with them and everything is like
like you know Walt Disney you know they
just everything about them looks like
Hello Kitty you know and you're like oh
man you know just you're around them and
you feel this deep deep affection for
them that's called Yong Yong jumo means
uh you want to get them stuff you want
them to have stuff okay and the person
that you most love in this world I don't
know about you but for
me uh most of my day is spent looking at
stuff that they might like you see most
of my day I went up uh I don't know
what's the Avenue what's the Avenue with
all the dress stores and stuff is it fit
Park what's to
thead it was Madison I think I don't
think it was fit fit goes downtown right
something coming Uptown it must be
fourth right Madison yeah so I'm
like oh they might no they would rather
no that yeah that one you know and then
uh you on Juma means you want to see
them happy you just want to pamper them
and give them things and anything they
wish for okay any you're like constantly
watching them and seeing what they would
like and then your whole
res benami how do you say
it your whole reason for being is
to is to get them the things they like
you know and it's a beautiful
feeling to have anyone in your life that
is like that you see uh to have someone
in your life that
you you get up in the morning and you're
just thinking of things they might enjoy
joy and things they might like and you
spend the day looking for things you
know and uh you're just always on the
lookout for something they might like
and it's not always a physical thing
like they might like it if you said a
kind word to someone or they might like
it if you felt love for somebody you see
like a
higher kind of pleasure giving okay it's
like your heart llama is like that right
they they love these little they like
little stuff okay you can take your
heart Lama r j loved
KitKat candy bars he didn't eat them he
gave them way to kids but it was his
favorite my teacher one of his favorite
things was KitKat candy bars so you know
you would go looking for Kit Kat candy
bars but then what he really enjoyed was
if you did something good you know if he
caught you doing something good he would
be really happy you see so you won't
jump out which number four it's like you
go through your whole day making small
mental and physical offerings to to your
llama or to your mother right and that's
the guy who's standing at the biscuit
cart okay so you just think you you
fantasize and you make offerings to your
mom over and over all day long and it's
a beautiful way to live you don't get
much done okay like you're always behind
on the homeworks and stuff uh but then
when I think about it it's a better way
to spend your life right it's more
important that you make these little
offerings of goodness to your heart
teacher then it is to finish your work
okay cuz that is your work that's the
more important work is to
love uh next one number five it's called
n say n n ning means heart J
means king or Lord the Lord of hearts
and ning
means you want
to
remove any suffering or trouble that
your mother might have you see so you
might want to you any you
anticipate any kind of problem another
person might have and you and you remove
it I like to do it anonymously I like to
do it proactively I like to remove their
problems before they're even aware of
the problem you see and they just never
hear about it you see like rimbe never
paid a bill you see my teacher didn't
pay any bills he thought he didn't have
any
bills he's like I don't know where he
thought the phone was coming
from uh but he never saw a phone bill
you see we just intercepted them and uh
he he got Social Security he never he
didn't know it took 48 trips to Social
Security he was like it's so nice for
the government to send me money every
month you know we're
like yeah like we fought them you know
and he never knew about it you see so
you just uh
intercept
problems uh for people around you for
whom for everybody okay because
everybody has been your mother
okay so that's kind of a big
responsibility right like I'm not
talking one person I'm talking all the
people around you because they've all
equally been your mother you can't say
this one was more my mother than that
one okay it's not logical okay each one
has been your mother and each one has
treated you equally okay kindly so I'm
not talking about the mother and this
this way and I'm not talking about the
first person you meet on 86th Street
when you leave the room tonight I'm
talking every single person around you
has equally paid you kindness and they
have given their life for you countless
times and you owe them okay so when I
talk about intercepting people's
problems uh it's for everybody okay
everybody around you all
right not just one person everybody
okay there's a debate by the way some
people
say uh this this teaching was
popularized by Lord Aisha and by kesi
chawa uh a thousand years ago they say
why why didn't they do the step of
taking away the problems before they did
the step of giving them sweet things
they said said uh if a child is sick
first you treat the child's illness and
then you give them toys you see you
don't go to a child who has a flu and
say here do you want a toy you know you
you treat them first and make them
better and then you give them a toy they
said it's backwards and then uh Lord AA
and other Lamas they said first you have
to feel
this special love towards them
and the desire that they be happy and
then you will want to treat them okay
like that there's a reason why it comes
in this order
okay number six is intense okay number
six is called
say and we talked about it yesterday we
had a program uh during the day
yesterday
uh it's the
decision that you yourself will take
personal
responsibility that no one in the world
has any pain and that no one in the
world misses any kind of happiness that
they could have you see like it's
difficult to take responsibility for one
other person's needs it's difficult for
us it's difficult okay to really like my
old lady you know we're having all these
discussions I I have an older uh woman
that I I help care for and uh we're
having all these discussions she uh is
getting too old to
drive okay like it's dangerous she's had
a couple of really bad accidents you
know the police took her uh license away
she she said I don't care what are they
going to do lock me up you know who's
going to lock off an 85-year-old lady
she gets in her car she drives around
you know
and uh they're afraid of her and uh you
and and it's dangerous you know and she
hits people and then uh no and we try to
it's you know we we met a man the other
day whose daughter was killed by an
elderly driver you know and we talked to
her we sat her down and we said look
this guy we both know his daughter was
killed by a an elder person who
shouldn't be driving you know but she
can't give it up and then there's all
this uh conversations going on about
well who's going to drive her around
when she needs groceries and who's going
to take her to see her friends and who's
going to take her to her chorus practice
and and then it's then it's suddenly
Dawning on everybody that you're talking
a lot of time you know uh it's not it's
one thing to take away her car it's
another thing to to coordinate all her
driving needs you know between what six
seven people and uh to take
responsibility for a single person's
needs is difficult okay in Step number
six we are proposing that you make a
commitment to take care of the needs of
countless
beings all right why why should
you what's in it for you why why do you
have any responsibility for them they've
been your mother okay they've been your
mother we have a student in the
threeyear
retreat uh in Arizona her mother had a
very serious
stroke and and she's uh incapacitated
she needs 24-hour care you know and then
we feel like we have to do it we're
taking care of her you know it's very
expensive and uh and it's difficult and
we we feel responsible to do it because
she's the mother of a of a close friend
you know and no one else is helping
so but everyone is that to you everyone
has been that to you and then you feel
overwhelmed right you feel like well
you're asking me to take responsibility
for
every the needs of every person in New
York it's not possible I cannot do it
okay and we're facing that with our old
ladies you know like the one old lady is
$2,500 a month you know and then the
other old lady is like a couple thousand
a month and we just don't have the money
nobody has the money you know and then
what are you going to do you know and
then you're proposing to me that I
should uh assume responsibility for the
needs of millions upon millions of
beings on this planet because they used
to be my mother you know you're asking
me you know I can't take care of tool
ladies now you now you want me to take
on a few million more you know and I
can't do it I don't have the capacity
okay then uh what do you call necessity
is the mother of
invention right if you really want to do
something a human being can find a way
okay if you have a burning desire to do
something you can do it okay you can do
anything all right a human being has the
capacity to take care of millions upon
millions of beings at the same time if
you were
driven by a love if you were driven by a
love that was strong enough you would
find a
way okay you would find a way if you
were driven hard enough if you wanted it
bad enough you would find a way you can
find the way okay what is the way open
the heart checker okay open the heart
chakra learn to split your
body okay learn to split your body
millions of times billions of times okay
learn to stand above an entire planet
and split enough bodies to take care of
every creature there under the right
pressure you could do it you have the
capacity and you just need
this you need the circumstances to force
you to it
okay circumstances will force you to
that and you will learn okay I I always
have people uh I have
friends uh they were married their whole
lives right they never learned to fix a
car or they never learned to fix a door
or you know what I mean like that and
then uh the guy left or they kicked the
guy out right 2 Days Later what's
happening they're out there fixing their
car and they're out there fixing the
door and it's not like they were
incapable before they just didn't have
to do it you know and anybody in this
room can do everything that everybody
else can do if you were forced to do it
you know you would learn and you would
do it okay if the drive was enough if
the desire was enough you would learn to
split your body you you because you're
capable of it you have the ability to
split your body
you just haven't been pushed to it yet
how do you get pushed to
it watch the guy on any6 strength this
is the beginning of the process it will
end in you splitting your body okay the
beginning is tonight the process starts
tonight you walk out on 86th Street the
first person you run
into just for a few moments think this
person was my mother I'm I'm responsible
for this this person this person is my
responsibility all of their needs
okay it's my responsibility okay and
that's enough for tonight that's enough
and then it will force you eventually it
will force you to learn to split your
body because you can you can do it you
have the capacity it's you just haven't
been pushed far enough okay so tonight
first person you meet out of the room
out of the building just look at them
and say I will I will you know I I will
gain the capacity to take care of
you okay cuz you've been my mother all
right and that's the whole meditation
that's the whole step seven is called
the bodh okay step seven is called bod
it
means I I will learn to split my body
for you okay and I will take care of you
right
like that all
right okay we'll take a break
uh I'll be here if somebody has a
burning question or I have one
meeting uh I have like a 10-minute
meeting and then uh if if you have some
questions okay leave them up here and
I'll announce them okay so I'm sorry to
keep you late and and we'll take a break
all right then we'll come back and we'll
do inner
body
okay so tonight we went through the
seven step
meditation to try to
develop uh love from the inside and now
uh we'll talk about the inner body
practices that you would use to try to
develop the same attitude by working
from the outside okay outside means uh
you would use ASAS
uh or you would use pranayamas
oras or bandas uh yogic techniques to
induce ultimate love all right and what
the meditation we did at the beginning
which I would like you to practice it's
on your homework for tonight did you get
your homework yeah so they ran
out they got the homework at 8:00 okay
they did a good job um tomorrow I'll
probably later okay
if that's possible
uh on your homework there's a meditation
that I'd like to ask you to do which is
breathing just breathing through your
chakras okay uh we're trying to open the
heart
chakra I'm going to give you a 20 minute
okay we only have 20 minutes more I
would like to give you a 20 minute
rundown on the heart chakra okay so they
say in Tibet to open a chakra or to to
get prom I'm moving to a chakra first
you have to understand the structure
what do they call it in in medicine
uh uh a a combination of organs which
are considered as a
group system there's another word for it
a structure or a compx I don't know it
bugs me I can't remember it it's like a
structure the the heart you have to
before we work on the heart chakra I
want you to understand the physiology of
the heart chakra okay the parts of the
heart chakra okay how it's built the
structure of the heart chakra okay which
is weird it's different okay and I think
I'd like to go at it through uh and I
put a translation there's the beginning
of a translation in your notebooks right
and there's much more coming tomorrow I
think there's 50 more pages coming
tomorrow okay and it's a it's part of a
translation I did a huge translation of
the inner body it was hundreds of pages
I gave uh some of it for one of the B
Jima classes we used I don't know 50
pages of it or 75 pages but there's
hundreds of pages uh from the classics
of the inner body and I'd like to go
over with you just what the heart chakra
looks
like uh particularly from birth okay how
does the heart chakra form uh in your in
the womb all right so if you understand
the physical structure of the heart
chakra see get the feeling of what we're
doing in the first half of the class we
tried emotionally to open the heart
chakra and now we're going to be like
surgeons and we're going to go into the
physical what's the word it sounds like
structure we're going to go into the
physical structure of the heart chakra
and talk about opening it
mechanically okay through pranayama or
through uh ASA yoga okay and and that's
CH that's working from the outside and
working from the inside which is faster
okay from the inside you're going to
open your heart in an emotional sense
with the seven step practice from the
outside you're going to learn the
structure the physical structure of the
heart chakra and then you're going to
work on just cutting it open okay
through yogic means all right uh so I
think it's a cool uh you have to
understand that in Tibet uh ultimately
you were required to do both you were
required to join together these two
approaches inner and outer okay it was
felt that you would never be able to
complete the job fast enough if you
didn't work from the outside and the
inside at the same time okay so so this
is a very high way of developing love
you you see it's very beautiful the idea
that you could uh work on a physical
structure of your body to become a
better person to become a nicer person
okay uh a Kinder person to develop that
Peak experience right where you have
direct perception of billions of beings
and you love them and you see how you
will take care of them right and the
idea that you could do some kind of
physical exercises that would open your
heart in conjunction with meditations
that open your heart emotionally it's a
beautiful uh and unique concept you know
I told my friend he's Christian priest I
said you know
in if if you were running your church
the way we are running things you'd be
doing push-ups during the sermon you
see uh you see the idea is is quite
literally you you do physical exercises
which tend to open the heart chakra to
do that you have to understand the
structure of the the heart chakra and to
do that I think it's most useful to go
at it by seeing how the heart chakra
forms in inside the womb uh as the child
forms the heart chakra also forms okay
so we're going to discuss that and it's
going to be a whirlwind discussion
otherwise you won't get
home so the we we we can say that in
this practice we are working with seven
chakras there are more okay sometimes
nine sometimes 10 we are working with uh
seven main chakras in trying to develop
love and of all the chakras the heart
chakra forms first in the womb okay as
the child develops uh the heart chakra
forms first how the other parts of the
inner body form which winds come first
which chakras come after the heart
chakra will give give you that also
maybe tomorrow okay you'll get it in
your reading all
right so the heart chakra forms first
there are two famous presentations on
the heart chakra one is
called uh
say that means the eight channel Petals
of the heart the eight channel petals of
the heart because the channels coming
out of the heart chakra resemble Petals
of a flower okay uh physically they look
more like spokes of a wheel coming out
of the heart chakra but they are given
the name of petals okay they don't look
like rose petals okay they look more
like Wagon
Wheel what do you call sticks spokes
okay but they are called petals okay so
it's a famous
principle of Tantra in Tibet that the
heart chakra has eight petals or eight
channels coming out of the heart chakra
eight primary channels okay we ain't
going to talk about that we are not
talking about that okay say
nar toar toar
CH G the eight channels which form at
the heart comma at the beginning we're
talking about those eight which is not
the same as the first dat okay the first
eight I mentioned you have in your heart
chakra now you have eight principal
channels coming out of your heart chakra
okay we ain't going to talk about this
so don't get confused that's why I'm
bringing it up to confuse you okay you
have eight chakra you have eight
channels coming out of your chakras now
we ain't going to talk about them we're
talking about the eight channels which
form inside the womb near the heart okay
cuz that's what we're interested in
we're interested in the dang there's a
medical
term you have to find it it sounds like
structure but it's not that it's a it's
a word
for the structure of an organ and it's
Associated organs but anyway uh we're
talking about
that not system it's something else it's
sounds weird it sounds like a business
terance I don't know anyway you'll find
it by
tomorrow so I'm going to go through the
eight channels that
form uh in your
heart uh when you are first uh born okay
I hang on one
sec yeah
okay I want to get it
right the first channel to develop is
the sushumna the central channel right
right in a grown person it extends from
here between the eyebrows under the
skull down uh outside the bottom of the
skull outside the inside of the bottom
of the skull okay extends down from the
inside of the bottom of the skull comes
down in front of the spine they say
within a half inch of the spine follows
The Spine down to the sexual organ and
terminates at the end of the sexual
organ okay so that's the
Suna sometimes it's called ATI okay uh
in Sanskrit in tibetan it's called sa
and there are 12 synonyms for it in
Sanskrit and they all mean like middle
Channel Central channel uh J in uh
Chinese okay these are different names
for uh the central channel that one
forms
first if you can get Prana to move
through the central Channel you will
have those experiences we talked about
you will see Ultimate Reality
directly uh your mind's capacity is open
to see directly the faces of billions of
creatures at the same moment and you
have an intense love for them an intense
desire to care for them like the two
little kids banging on the bathroom door
okay you have if you can get Prana to
enter the central Channel
say timum Tim shuk Means enter name
means stay Tim Means melt or dissolve if
you can get Prana to go through these
three stages
inside the central Channel which
requires opening the heart chakra
okay then you can have those Peak
experiences we talked about your mind is
open completely and your heart is open
completely you can see billions of
creatures at the same time this is
before you become a Buddha okay much
longer before and
you're and you and you see Ultimate
Reality the say if you can get Prana
into the central Channel we said
yesterday for most people almost no
Prana travels through their Central
Channel it is blocked primarily by the
knots at the heart
okay what causes the knots at the heart
okay there there's the main Channel Suna
Central Channel
and then on each side starting here okay
here are the termination points uh there
are two side channels smaller channels
okay they go this
way and then they cross over here and
come back and then they continue under
the skull they cross over here at the
tip of the head they continue down to
the back of the bottom of the neck in
front of the spine and they cross over
again choking the central Channel okay
and in the monastery we don't have time
but they they demonstrate this with
three rosaries and the Llama ends up
like this you
know you know and uh when it reaches the
heart CH chakra which is not at the
heart don't think front of your body in
the in the monastery they hit you with a
rosary if you ever go like this heart
chakra you get hit you learn to go like
this uh it's in front of the spine
at the level of the heart and that's why
it's called heart ja it is not in the
heart okay
uh there the side channels twist around
three times okay it's the hardest chakra
to open uh and then they twist around
again main the main chakra behind the
navl uh and swana at the base of the
spine and then once more at the grin
these are the major chakras okay knots
knots formed by the side channels
um they list the first one side channel
to grow in the womb as the pingala okay
pingala is running it's the one that
starts on the right side of your nose by
the way that's why you have two
nostrils the structures of your body
form around the channels the reason you
have two nostrils is that there's two
channels here okay if you could
eliminate them you'd probably have one
big hole here
okay uh so this channel is called
pingala in Sanskrit it's called Uh INB
betan it's called Roma say Roma ROM uh
that's a translation of rasana which
means uh the channel of taste or a
bitter red hot channel in the yoga Sut
what's this channel
called
s that got okay in the heart in sorry in
the yoga Su it's called the sun channel
right uh so that comes from the right
side and twists around and continues
like that okay its color is
red you can say a dark pink and that's
why it's called pink G okay pinka came
into English as pink
okay if Prana that's the second channel
of the how many eight which form in the
area of the heart at the beginning okay
uh because in the beginning all there is
is this much of your body you see there
is no head yet this is before the
appearance of the five what we call the
five Yen loock the two two arms two legs
and the head even before they start to
bump out uh you already have this
structure in your heart okay so at that
point the the central channel is about
this long it's just a piece it's a
little piece right okay and uh then
comes the pingala already wrapped around
the central Channel all right already
choking the central channel in the womb
in the first month of gestation
okay when Prana moves through the right
hand Channel you feel angry or you feel
upset all right that's a red channel
pingala
channel it's sometimes called the
channel of the
grasp uh in the
vaj what's it
called
right means the channel through which
your misunderstanding of objects Channel
travels Zin means the channel through
which your misunderstanding of people
travels
and they are both called Ching or more
correctly
Ching which means Ivy I what do you call
Vine Vines of Ivy
why they grow around your central
channel from the first month of
gestation they're already wrapped around
your main Channel like a ivy okay and
they choke it right so when when you
feel upset or angry Prana is moving
through the pingala the right hand
Channel all
right the more upset you get the more it
will choke the central Channel and the
less likely you will be to have the two
perceptions
of emptiness and love okay the more
upset you get in
traffic the more you disqualify yourself
from having a deep meditative experience
3 days
later it's not going to happen okay if
you get reasonable irritated in traffic
there's enough Prana coming into the
pingala that you will never be able to
go into a deep meditation within the
next 72 hours not possible okay if you
get irritated every
day then you're in
trouble all right okay so even in the
womb in the first month already the
pingala has formed and it is already
started to choke the little inch of the
central Channel okay uh uh in the womb
okay uh on the left the next channel to
form which is how many we
got yeah now we're on the third okay in
Sanskrit it's called ID say ID if you
want to sound exactly
correct curl your tongue back and
say and say ha yoga yog and say mandala
Manda and say
band and this is the correct uh way to
put your tongue okay and then you will
sound Indian Okay the reason Indian
sounds Indian is cuz they are making
rlex sounds properly correctly so it's
not ID and it's not ha yoga it's say
hat okay means sheep okay it's hard to
find that uh translation it's in the
Tibetan scriptures okay ITA means a
sheep why because that channel which is
also called Chandra which means Moon the
Moon uh it's a white color it's a milky
white color they are both by the way
what do you call it opaque they are not
crystallin in color they are impure
channels and they are opaque they are
also damaged all right they are always
damaged they have tears in them they are
crooked uh the scriptures describe the
two side channels as being defective
okay so when you
uh want something really bad I call it
Pringle Channel okay Pringle means I
don't mean if you've ever met a person
who really knows how to eat they open a
can of Pringles they take one Pringle
this is like
anat and they enjoy it they really enjoy
it and they might even put back the last
half and then they cover it and they
feel happy and they feel satis fine okay
The Prana in that moment is moving
through which
channel enjoyment true enjoyment honest
clean happy enjoyment it's moving to the
central Channel okay but people like me
you know then you're
like and it's this problem because they
flop against
your they kind of hit you in the
nose you're trying to scoop them in you
know I'm true at the same time
and you just get out of
control you you can't enjoy them you
don't enjoy them you're not enjoying
them you're just nervous like you're
something nervous like you have a
meeting in an hour and you're late and
you didn't eat yet and you're just
like okay when you go from enjoyment to
nervous The Prana moves into the ID okay
The Prana has moved into the IT nervous
eating nervous desire for anything what
do you call it unhappy desire
okay uh then that's then The Prana is
moving through the even in a child in
the womb in the first month emotions are
flowing there is there is a feeling of
they say there's a feeling of
constriction and feeling hot and feeling
a little bit upset about that and then
they they say there's a feeling of uh
wanting to get out really bad and and
those two emotions already in a child in
the first first month are choking the
central channel the two side channels
are choking I'm talking now about the
structure of your heart chakra right so
now you have three components of
this system or structure I forget the
word okay uh this thing called the heart
chakra okay we already have three parts
of the heart chakra okay next one to
form it's called The Lady of the triple
turn which is called sum
in in tibetan okay the lady of the
triple
turn this is a
channel which bursts out of the area of
the central Channel towards the front
Okay towards the front of the body okay
if you take a garden
host and can I go a little bit late is
it okay yes
sorry uh is it really okay if it's not
okay just leave but don't forget the
first person you meet okay um
if you take a garden hose and you kink
it right and then you turn open the
valve there will be a buildup of water
right and if you keep insisting and you
don't open the kink in the valve it will
burst it will split right that's what
happens to the central Channel when it
is choked by the triple turn around it
of the of the two side channels and it
and it bursts the pr bursts out and it
goes straight the first Channel goes
straight horizontally right towards the
front of the body which in which in
spiritual terms in Asia is always
considered which
direction the East okay the front of the
body is called the East what's the back
of the
body what's the Sanskrit word for
West so if you do
aim you are stretching the West Side the
back side of the body okay and P came
into V came into W GES into West so West
comes from P okay uh so the first
channel uh to break out after the first
three have formed is the Eastern Channel
and it's called The Lady of the triple
term turn
Suma the next pedal is the called the
lady of
desire which in tibetan is called uh F
Duma and sorry dma and it comes to the
South which would be what side of your
body the right side okay so just I have
trouble I'm like dyslexic on directions
I always think I'm standing in Kansas
and I'm facing New York City okay that's
how I remember I can't remember the
colors of all the five Buddhist and all
that unless I go in Kansas and stand
facing New York and then I think okay
Texas is the South okay so you know the
right channel bursts out next okay due
to the pressure at the heart okay the
right channel bursts out
next the next uh channel is called um
Kima say Kima K the lady of the
home and it breaks to the West breaks
out to the West okay which would be the
back of your body towards the back of
your body you are still less than an
inch
long okay where talking inside the womb
in the first month of gestation these
how many channels we up to six channels
okay guess which channel is
next
Canada okay all right that's how I
remember it okay Canada is coming out to
the left okay I'm in Kansas I'm facing
New York and and Canada breaks out to
the left the name of that uh channel is
called Tumo which is not the same as the
Tumo at your Naval chakra okay it means
the lady of fire okay the lady of
fire so try to imagine the
structure the it's called process it's
called process yeah and it doesn't mean
a series of events it means a structure
an organ structure it's called the heart
process okay check it out in anatomy
it's called a pro a process meaning uh a
a thing composed of many pieces and
performing a single function is called
the heart process okay so so now you
have how many you have six components to
the process or to the structure of the
heart chakra right then there's this
weird uh
Channel say djama djama djama djama do
means a demon
okay in tibetan do means a demon yaka
chel means don't possess m means a lady
and then if you study the tantas
extensively they come to explain this
channel you could translate it as the
the lady demon of obstruction okay the
lady demon of obstruction gel in this
case means obstruction okay and this is
a weird
uh auxiliary channel that runs together
with the central Channel it runs very
close to the central Channel okay in an
adult it terminates at the
throat uh and it terminates at the navl
okay so it's short it only covers the
length of your torso
okay and and from what I have found
it's an attempt uh for The Prana to
bypass the knot created by that two side
channels okay it's an attempt by your
body uh to create a substitute Channel
through which Prana can bypass the heart
which is blocked okay so now youve got
this vision of the heart chakra okay the
process of the heart chakra it's a
central Channel it has two side channels
choking it because they turn around it
three times each of
them it's like that medical symbol they
made is it a masas or something the this
thing some people say it might be a an
ancient representation of the heart
chuckra I don't know but it's three
turns around the central channel that
chokes the central Channel then come one
by one these side channels four side
channels
okay and then there's an attempt by the
body to bypass it and there's a there's
another weird Channel an eighth Channel
grows even in a baby even in a child and
you keep that channel throughout your
life
okay you okay yeah is it possible that
if if there was a lot of trauma and then
a physical disease that a person who has
uh whose PR has desperately tried to
circum that would possibly feel
constricted at the throat later in life
or have stomach issues yeah it's very
possible yeah it's very possible yeah
constrictions of The
Prana by other
channels uh which obstruct the free flow
of Prana
right can be triggered by emotions and
then they lead to medical problems they
lead to physical problems they underly
tumors for
example uh a tumor is based on a kink
inary
Channel okay like
that so we have
eight uh components of the heart Channel
and try to get a feeling tonight I don't
I think that's all I can do uh let me do
a little bit more okay I'm just going to
go okay I I don't get here very often
and I don't get a chance to talk about
these things you guys some people here
are 10 years into this and it's kind of
satisfying for me cuz otherwise I have
to go to Ukraine and talk
about you know guess what things are
coming from you you know and you know
and the people who travel with me they
fall asleep I say guess what they fall
asleep you know cuz they heard it 3,000
times I don't get to go very far with
people very often okay so
anyway uh
this is what's happening to your heart
chakra now and there is
a there's a blockage in your heart
chakra uh a a problem which has been
with you since the day you were born
okay you've had this problem this
problem with your heart chakra has
existed since the day you were born I
mean before in the womb N 9 months
before the day you were born you were
born with this with a blocked heart
chakra
okay and that's why okay
now what travels through the four we we
talked about what travels through the
central Channel when you feel love when
you feel knowledge when you have
understanding Prana is moving through
the central Channel okay when you're in
a traffic jam and you're angry can you
turn it down a bit uh when you're in a
traffic jam and you're angry uh Prana is
moving to the right hand Channel and
choking the central Channel when you're
on your 10th Pringle or your 10th
Pringle
package uh then I'm talking Mahana
that's I'm Mahana uh great capacity but
um but
uh then then the pr moving through the
left hand Channel and choking the
central channel it's not you're not
physically capable of having a kind
thought try to get used to that kind of
thinking you are not physically capable
of having a kind thought all right
because it's being choked then the four
channels shoot out of the area of the
heart right uh North sorry east south
west and north right what kind of Prana
is traveling through those channels we
call the four elements okay say
sa sa ch ch me
okay uh earth water fire and wind okay
don't think Earth fire water and wind
are some kind of stupid medical system
from the Medieval Times okay it's not
like that it isn't some doctor in uh
1300s in in England didn't understand
the body and decided you were having a a
problem of your bile humor or something
okay don't think like that these are
very very profound understanding of the
very underpinning of all existence okay
satu are not dirt water what do you call
to
H and Chi okay even in China they have
right it's not don't think it's some
kind of stupid thing that they think
there's dirt inside of you or something
like that it's not that the element of
Earth is the very fact that any two
objects could come together it's like a
gravitational force okay an element of
earth when they say element of Earth
it's the cohesiveness which holds all
objects together and prevents them from
falling apart okay it's the cohesive
energy it's a Electric magnetic force
which holds objects together okay that's
the element of Earth it's not some
stupid medieval thing okay Chu means the
capacity of things to
move uh or to be to be wet or to be
fluid okay the
the the energy of fluidity is called the
element of water in ancient times okay
the fact that the thing could flow okay
then what would may be Fire
H fire the the fact of heat okay the
fact of heat what do you call absolute
cold
and okay it's it's the fact of
temperature in the universe it's called
called the element of fire don't think
it's some stupid thing it's it's
the it's the energy which creates the
universe and creates the heat of the
universe and creates the univer creates
the energy of Life creates the heat of
life it it is a power it's a it's an
extraordinary power which creates the
very temperature of the universe okay of
every sun in the universe
okay and then the power of wind all
motility all motion the moving of any
object from Atomic subatomic particles
to planets and to galaxies is the is the
element of wind okay now get this this
is the cool thing all
right as PR passes through those four
channels in your body in the womb when
you are 1 in long they create the
universe around
you try to grasp that okay the movement
of Prana through the four channels
coming out of the heart linked to the
elements the elemental forces creates
the galaxies that exist around you when
you are
born
cool extraordinary try to understand
okay the universe is is
derived the measurable
universe that you now are at the center
of right is is flowing from those four
channels at your
heart okay try to grasp that okay later
those channels split okay each one of
the four splits to the
right the one running to New York splits
to
Florida okay get used to it all right
the one that's supposed to go to Texas
splits to Arizon Arizona the one going
to California branches off toon Oregon
and the one going to Canada goes to
Maine all right got it uh they don't
split off at the heart they split off a
little further down okay uh so a another
channel the the main four continue in
the in the straight Direction but then
another one splits off of each one
okay that's how you get the eight
channels of the heart got it which are
not the eight channels that form in the
heart area
in gestation right we started by talking
about eight channels of the heart in a
fully developed person there are eight
channels coming to the heart there's
four main channels then there's one
extra Channel off of each one splitting
off to the right why are they important
why am I talking about this okay why are
we staying up late to do this I got to
get up early and I have a party after
this
okay but I'll make it uh
I have locked some okay
uh inside the channels that split to
Florida Arizona Oregon and Maine
okay run your capacity of sense runs
Your Capacity to to be aware of anything
of of the outer World okay to see things
to smell things to hear things to taste
things
the primary channels of the heart are
creating the universe and the secondary
channels of the heart are creating your
experience of the universe it's cool
okay your whole experience of the
universe and the universe itself are
flowing out of eight tiny channels at
the heart that are there when you are
only an inch
big okay got it that's pretty awesome
okay all right okay just get yeah so so
is that the choking that creates all of
this then yeah the choking creates it
yeah so is that a curse or is that a
we'll get there she wants to know if all
this is being cre created by choking
then is that a bad thing it is a bad
thing okay the universe as it stands is
a bad thing okay worlds worlds which
will die Suns which will burn out in
inhabitants of Worlds who will die
inhabitants of Worlds who are doomed to
be born and to die okay and to lose all
the things they worked for their whole
life okay and all their loved ones yeah
it's a curse okay uh it can be fixed the
point is to fix it okay it doesn't have
to be like that but that's a that's a
good question that's
sansara okay what's happening what's
being produced by the heart chakra
channels is is the world of suffering
and the universe of suffering a universe
in which planets burn out Suns burn out
and the Ants crawling across the surface
of each planet continually die get old
lose everything they want including us
we're one of them right okay okay got
it uh is there anything else I have to
depress you
about
uh yeah okay last
thing
uh
so it follows upon your question what
would happen if we loosen the channels
at the heart what would happen if we
were able to loosen the choke hold on
the channels of Heart by the way the
word chakra you know means a wheel and
it refers to the image of spokes coming
out of a hub when you look down the
central channel on this structure on
this
process you see eight spks radiating out
and that's why they're called chakras
okay that's why they're given the name
chakras which means Wagon Wheels right
so looking down the central Channel you
see the eight Spooks coming out and and
that's that's why they're called chras
that's why they're given the name chakra
don't say Shakra Shakra is an evil demon
that lived in India couple thousand
years ago he's not a chakra okay chakra
is chakra Shakra is chakra okay I don't
know how you got called shakras anyway
uh last question then we'll go home or
to a party or wherever
uh if you could loosen the strangle hold
of the two side channels on the central
Channel if you could break the vines off
the pillar right by the way there's
another name for the central channel in
Sanskrit which is aad Duty okay and
there was a famous Yogi whose name was a
Duty you get to study his text someday
okay other means off duty means throw it
off it refers to te ripping the side
channels off of the main Channel get off
of me get off of me like that you see
when you tear the side channels off of
the main Channel that's called aad dutti
and then the central Channel opens and
it and the hard Channel opens so get
this three things happen three things
happen one first you see emptiness
directly
okay you see emptiness
directly secondly you have that
experience of ultimate love okay you
have that experience of ultimate
love
thirdly the process by which the
channels of the heart create the world
around you and create your perception of
the world is
purified and you enter a holy
Paradise you see the world trans
transforms and your body transforms and
you become a being of light and the
world around you becomes pure because
there's no more choke on the central
Channel actually the channels the four
channels withdraw and the two channels
withdraw and that little auxiliary
Channel with jaws and they all suck into
the middle and then the world is pure
then you live in a pure World okay no
death no war no hunger no sadness no
unhappiness okay a world where of
perfect
happiness and try to appreciate that you
have gotten there through physical means
we have we have operated on this process
of the
heart okay and so we'll continue
tomorrow obviously we need to talk more
about the we talked about the problem
now we have to talk about the physical
and inner practices by which you repair
this process this system at the heart
how are we going to open it and how we
going to release the channels which will
cause a corresponding transformation in
your body and your world got it it's
very cool right you still need the first
meditation okay that's the inner method
and then you need the outer method okay
which means after you walk out of
here first person you meet in the subway
who doesn't have a knife okay or
something okay all right okay all right
let's dedicate the karma uh Mr huitt
will you leave the thing
wait
s
part
G
sh
to
uh let me
see uh 7:15 tomorrow uh homework groups
out here if you like or you are
commanded to approach
somebody in the class that you don't
know and go to a coffee shop together or
something like that uh Second
if uh if you finish all the work you'll
get a certificate and I would like you
to teach okay so please work hard learn
all the material work with your taas
they have all the what do you call them
homework Masters and then they'll guide
you and and they'll make sure you know
everything well okay so do the homeworks
all right and you'll have another
homework tomorrow if you finish it you
get a
certificate uh eventually and then no
we'll get you one soon and then what was
the other thing if you have a yamantaka
empowerment uh please talk
to Nani who's you want to uh because
tonight is the black moon and there
would be
a uh there will be a ceremony tonight
for y Mana okay so uh see you tomorrow
thank you very very much because it's a
very uh for me it it's very very uh I
feel very happy to talk about these
things and very uh grateful that there
are good people to listen to it okay so
good night
yeah